Guide to the Madagascar Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Madagascar collection
1930-2013
1973-1983
MS 1527
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.27
(6 boxes)
The collection consists of an essay, printed material, and photographs relating to the history of Madagascar and political and social conditions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of an essay, printed material, and photographs relating to the history of Madagascar and political and social conditions.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Madagascar; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- Madagascar; Madagascar -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Madagascar -- Foreign relations -- United States; Madagascar -- History -- Hova rule, 1810-1885; Madagascar -- Politics and government; Madagascar -- Social conditions; United States -- Foreign relations -- Madagascar
- Inventory, 1973-1983
  - "British Involvement in Madagascar in the Nineteenth Century": an essay by Stephen Garfink, 1973 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Periodicals: information and opinion, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Indian Ocean and Madagascar: journals; magazines, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO): printed material, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Un Aperçu des Relations Américano-Malagasy: Centenaire du Traité Américano-Malagasy de Paix, d'Amitié et de Commerce", 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, 1930-1990; Accession 1995-M-191
  - "Conditions of life, work, and struggle of transport and port workers in Africa and Madagascar" [World Federation of Trade Unions], 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Evening Pioneer [first British daily newspaper in Madagascar], 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Une longue marche de 4000 jours [Comité National d'Observation des Elections(KMF/CNOE)], [1990?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Manifeste d'un nouvel ordre politique" by Rivoson Ratianarimanana, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Madagascar, [1930?] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    General
    About fifty scenes of the capital, port, and people, with French captions.
- Additional Material, 1975-1982; Accession 2004-M-074
  - Newspapers
    - Afaka, 1975 December, 1977 Mar, Jun, Jul, Oct, December (Box 1)
    - Ako Takariva, 1976 October (Box 1)
    - Alimanakan'ny Mpanao Gazety, 1975 February (Box 1)
    - Fanatanjahantena sy Fialamboly, 1977 April (Box 1)
    - Fandraharahana Fonja, 1978 June (Box 1)
    - Fandriampahalemana, 1976 October, 1981 October (Box 1)
    - Fararano Gazety, 1982 July (Box 1)
    - Firaisana, 1979 January
    - Gazety Herin' Andriamanitra, 1979 April (Box 1)
    - Gazety Vavolombelona, 1976 October (Box 1)
    - The Graphic, 1982 December, 1984 December (Box 1)
    - Ny Gazety Malagasy, 1983 May (Box 1)
    - Ndao, 1980 April (Box 1)
    - Revolution Malagasy, 1982 November (Box 1)
    - Vavolombelona, 1979 July (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1977, 2004; Accession 2010-M-109
  - Afrique-Madagascar-Promotion, Codiam, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Guide Statistique de Poche sur la Comptabilité Nationale, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Guide Statistique de Poche sur les Indices des Prix à la Consommation, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional material, 1997-2000s; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1997-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Posters, 2000s (Folder 2)